<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: javascript, | Joel Hooks]]></title>
  <link href="http://joelhooks.com/blog/categories/javascript/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://joelhooks.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-30T13:19:35-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://joelhooks.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joel Hooks]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Configuring Dependency Injection in AngularJS]]></title>
    <link href="http://joelhooks.com/blog/2013/08/18/configuring-dependency-injection-in-angularjs/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-18T12:45:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://joelhooks.com/blog/2013/08/18/configuring-dependency-injection-in-angularjs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dependency injection is the act of supplying values or object instances (dependencies) to target objects
from outside of the target object. In many (most?) cases this is automated
by a framework, such as AngularJS.</p>

<p>This means that a given target object does <strong>not</strong> create its own dependencies,
through the use of the <code>new</code> keyword or other creation methods.</p>

<p>By creating and managing dependencies
outside of an object, it makes it much easier to switch out that dependency as
needed. This is very useful when you are writing your unit tests, and can have
many advantages in larger systems.</p>

<p>There are only three ways for an object to resolve its dependencies:</p>

<ul>
<li>internally, via the <code>new</code> operator</li>
<li>lookup via a global variable (requirejs is an example)</li>
<li>the dependency is passed to the object</li>
</ul>


<p>The third option is <em>dependency injection</em>, and it is the preferred approach in
AngularJS apps.</p>

<h2>Defining your dependencies</h2>

<p>Dependency injection is a core feature of AngularJS. There are 3 approaches to
defining your dependencies, ordered by complexity from least to most:</p>

<ul>
<li>module.service</li>
<li>module.factory</li>
<li>module.provider</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>note:</strong> <em>AngularJS also provides <code>value</code> and <code>constant</code> dependencies. We aren&rsquo;t
going to get into those two today.</em></p>

<p>Both <code>service</code> and <code>factory</code> are abstractions that sit on top of <code>provider</code>.
Using <code>factory</code> and <code>provider</code> will give you more flexibility, but are more
verbose.</p>

<p>Before we look at how to use these tools, let&rsquo;s take a look at the AngularJS
source code and understand how they work.</p>

<h3>Interlude into the AngularJS internals</h3>

<p>If you&rsquo;re a geek like me, you might be curious as to what is going on under the hood
when you declare dependencies.</p>

<p>I mentioned earlier that <code>service</code> and <code>factory</code> were abstractions on top of <code>provider</code>.
To show you exactly how that works, we need to open up <code>injector.js</code> in <code>src/auto/</code>
folder in the AngularJS source code:</p>

<p>``` javascript
  function provider(name, provider_) {</p>

<pre><code>if (isFunction(provider_) || isArray(provider_)) {
  provider_ = providerInjector.instantiate(provider_);
}
if (!provider_.$get) {
  throw $injectorMinErr('pget', "Provider '{0}' must define $get factory method.", name);
}
return providerCache[name + providerSuffix] = provider_;
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>  function factory(name, factoryFn) { return provider(name, { $get: factoryFn }); }</p>

<p>  function service(name, constructor) {</p>

<pre><code>return factory(name, ['$injector', function($injector) {
  return $injector.instantiate(constructor);
}]);
</code></pre>

<p>  }
```</p>

<p>As you can see at a glance, <code>service</code> calls <code>factory</code> which calls <code>provider</code>. So, when it
gets right down to it, these three methods are the exact same thing. Convenient!</p>

<p>Almost the exact same thing.</p>

<p>There is a subtle difference. The AngularJS <code>service</code> uses
<code>$injector.instantiate</code> on the constructor function that you pass in. This means
that internally the <code>service</code> creates an instance of your function with the
<code>new</code> operator. This will provide the resulting object a valid &lsquo;this&rsquo; scope.</p>

<p>Using <strong><code>factory</code> doesn&rsquo;t call <code>new</code> on the function that is passed in</strong>.
When using <code>factory</code>, the function that is passed in is called directly, and an
object is expteded to be returned.</p>

<p>Hat tip to
<a href="http://twitter.com/ThomasBurleson">@ThomasBurleson</a> for pointing this
out. This can be confusing if encountered in the wild. Now you know.
Half the battle.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s start with the simplest use case. The <code>service</code>.</p>

<h3>Defining a service in AngularJS</h3>

<p>A service instantiates a constructor function.</p>

<p>``` javascript
(function(angular) {</p>

<pre><code>var module = angular.module("myApp.myModel", []);

var MyModel = function MyModel(asyncService) {
    return {
        someApi: function() {
            return asyncService.getStuff(); 
        }
    };
}

module.service('myModel', ['asyncService', MyModel]); //simple option
</code></pre>

<p>}(angular))
```</p>

<p>In this example we are creating a module that will store a model that grabs data from some asynchronous
service. The <code>myModel</code> service will return an instance of <code>MyModel</code> when it is requested
for injection by other objects. The instance of <code>MyModel</code> is a singleton, and only one instance will
ever be created and used by the application.</p>

<p>This example could actually be even simpler if the injectable doesn&rsquo;t require any additional
dependencies.</p>

<p><code>javascript
module.service('myModel',  MyModel); //most simple option
</code></p>

<p><code>module.service</code> requires only two arguments. A string for its unique name, and a constructor
to create an instance of. This approach is useful, and most of the time is probably all you need
for your application.</p>

<p>When you need more flexibility than the <code>service</code> provides, it is time to look at <code>factory</code>.</p>

<h3>Defining a factory in AngularJS</h3>

<p>A factory returns an object.</p>

<p>``` javascript
(function(angular) {</p>

<pre><code>var module = angular.module("myApp.myModel", []);

var MyModel = function MyModel(asyncService) {
    return {
        someApi: function() {
            return asyncService.getStuff(); //promise?
        }
    }
}

module.factory('myModel', ['asyncService', function (asyncService) {
    //could do some stuff here
    return new MyModel(asyncService); 
}]);
</code></pre>

<p>}(angular))
```</p>

<p>Using a <code>factory</code> provides additional flexibility. By providing a factory function
over a straight constructor, you are provided with the opportunity to do some work
prior to returning the object. You are also in charge of creating the
instance that you want returned, unlike <code>service</code>, which creates the
instance for the constructor function you provide.</p>

<p>The above example is obviously not
doing anything interesting, but when you need to do some work prior to resolving a
dependency, a factory can be a good choice.</p>

<p>In the real world, I&rsquo;ve used <code>factory</code> to provide a configurable mock data &ldquo;mode&rdquo;. The
factory function would check to see which mode the app was in, and dynamically switch
between mock and real data. This can be incredibly handy when you want to work with out
depending on external services.</p>

<p>Note that the factory function will be called exactly <strong>one time</strong>. Any work you do
will only be done once, and <code>myModel</code> will be whatever your factory function returns.
In this case, we are simply returning an instance of <code>MyModel</code>, but a factory can return
objects <em>and</em> functions. Use that to your advantage.</p>

<p>The last way to define dependencies is with <code>provider</code>. Let&rsquo;s look at that next.</p>

<h3>Defining a provider with AngularJS</h3>

<p>``` javascript
(function(angular) {</p>

<pre><code>var module = angular.module("myApp.myModel", []);

var MyModel = function MyModel() {
    return {
        asyncService: null,
        someApi: function {
            return this.asyncService.getStuff(); //promise?
        }
    }

}

var myModelProvider = {
    model: new MyModel();
    $get: ['asyncService', function (asyncService) {
        this.model.asyncService = asyncService; //"manual" dependency injection
        return this.model; //resolved for the lifetime of app
    }]
};

modules.provider('myModel', myModelProvider);
</code></pre>

<p>}(angular))
```</p>

<p>As you can see, <code>provider</code> is lower level. Explicit and verbose. The <code>$get</code> function
is used by AngularJS internally for the injector. A provider is <strong>required</strong> to have a <code>$get</code>
function. When using <code>factory</code> (and <code>service</code> as well) the <code>$get</code> function is defined for
you.</p>

<p>For all practical purposes you will likely never need to use <code>provider</code> unless you are a
control freak. In most circumstances a <code>factory</code> or <code>service</code> will suffice, but it is nice
to know that <code>provider</code> is there, if you needed that level of explicit control for some reason.</p>

<p>One thing to note about providers is that the provider is <em>available during <strong>configuration phase</strong> of a module</em>. While I haven&rsquo;t found a specific use case for this, it is something to have in your toolbox.</p>

<h3>A little trick for dynamic dependencies</h3>

<p>I mentioned before that with a <code>factory</code> (or <code>provider</code>) you can return an object or a function.
As it turns out, this can be very useful if you need to dynamically update a resolved dependency.
Here&rsquo;s a simple example using a factory.</p>

<p>``` javascript
module.factory(&lsquo;myDynamicInjectable&rsquo;, function () {</p>

<pre><code>    var count = 0;
    return function() {
        count = count +1;
        return count;
    }
});
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>This is an extremely trivial example, but now when you inject <code>myDynamicInjectable</code> and call it,
it will return the freshly incremented <code>count</code>.</p>

<p><strong>warning:</strong> <em>don&rsquo;t do this. There are two things wrong with this example. It is storing state
with the count variable, and then it is manipulating state. This isn&rsquo;t the appropriate location
for either of those activities! A better solution would be to create an object that stored
that state and provided a nice API for manipulating it.</em></p>

<p>A more realistic (useful) use of this might look like this:</p>

<p>``` javascript
module.factory(&lsquo;getCurrentShoppingCart&rsquo;, [&lsquo;getCurrentAccount&rsquo;, function(getCurrentAccount) {</p>

<pre><code>return function() {
    //getCurrentAccount is also a factory that returns a function
    //perhaps a user can have multiple accounts?
    return getCurrentAccount().shoppingCart;
}
</code></pre>

<p>}]);
```</p>

<p>There is a ton of dynamic flexibility you can take advantage of when returning functions from
both the <code>provider</code> and <code>factory</code> approaches. I&rsquo;d proceed with caution. You could easily abuse this
flexibility. Don&rsquo;t use this approach to manipulate and/or store state in the providers! The
job of these tools is to <strong>resolve dependencies</strong>, and should be used only to <strong>resolve dependencies</strong>.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>AngularJS provides several ways to configure dependency injection. From the simple <code>service</code> to the more flexible
<code>factory</code> and <code>provider</code> approaches. You should have a solid understanding of how these work
under the hood, and what situations are appropriate for each method.</p>

<p>P.S. This article is the expansion of the answer to a question that was emailed to me.
If you have any questions, I&rsquo;d love to help you out. My email and twitter can be found below, and I
answer them all.</p>

<p><strong>Related:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="/blog/2013/05/01/when-is-a-singleton-not-a-singleton/">AngularJS, Dependency Injection, and When Is a Singleton Not a Singleton?</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/2013/04/24/modeling-data-and-state-in-your-angularjs-application/">Modeling Data and State in Your AngularJS Application</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learn AngularJS this Weekend]]></title>
    <link href="http://joelhooks.com/blog/2013/08/03/learn-angularjs-in-a-weekend/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-03T23:36:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://joelhooks.com/blog/2013/08/03/learn-angularjs-in-a-weekend</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>AngularJS has a reputation for a steep learning curve. It&rsquo;s definitely complex, but follows the 80/20 rule. <strong>20% of the features are what you will use 80% of the time</strong>. If you are new to AngularJS and have a weekend to study, there are some very high quality resources that will let you <strong>start Monday with a strong working knowledge of AngularJS</strong>.</p>

<p>Already know AngularJS? Feel free to skip ahead. These resources are excellent, and you&rsquo;re bound to learn something.</p>

<h2>The Official Tutorial ~4hrs</h2>

<p>Start with <a href="http://docs.angularjs.org/tutorial">the official tutorial</a>. It provides a very straight forward overview of AngularJS and walks step by step through building a simple app. When you&rsquo;re done, you should have <strong>a solid understanding of the basics</strong> and the vocabulary you will need to move on to the next step.</p>

<p>The official tutorial is <em>very</em> well put together. Unfortunately it utilizes the angular-seed project as a template. The angular-seed project is fine for quickly throwing together a working AngularJS app, but it doesn&rsquo;t provide a structure that scales well in a production application.</p>

<p><strong>Don&rsquo;t use the angular-seed to start your real projects!</strong> It&rsquo;s a learning tool only.</p>

<h2>Kickass (<strong>free!</strong>) Video Tutorials on Egghead.io ~3hrs</h2>

<div style="float: left; padding:10px;"><a class="nofancybox" href="http://egghead.io"><div style=" height: 191px; width: 150px; background-image: url(/images/egghead_logo.png);"></div></a></div>


<p>You&rsquo;ve done the tutorial, and should have a good grasp of the basics. Your next stop is John Lindquist&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.egghead.io/">egghead.io for free AngularJS videos</a>. This series of bite-sized videos will deliver a ton of great information. John has gone through almost all of the &ldquo;hard&rdquo; concepts, and presented them in an easy to understand way.</p>

<p><em>All</em> of the videos are great, but the <strong>series on directives is extra fantastic</strong>. Transclusion? No problem. Even after using AngularJS for over a year, I was able to solidify some of the concepts that were confusing for me.</p>

<p>Watch them all and <strong>take some notes</strong>. When you come out of the other side your AngularJS-fu will be starting to take shape.</p>

<p><img src="/images/lemonade.jpg" alt="ahhhhhhh Learning AngularJS is refreshing - Photo Credit: chotda" /></p>

<p>That will take you through Saturday evening, and you deserve a rest. <strong>Send John a donation for his hard work</strong>, pour a tall glass of lemonade, and relax as you reflect on the your new-found knowledge of an awesome framework. Nice work!</p>

<h2>Things get real with angular-app ~4hrs</h2>

<p>Sunday morning.</p>

<p>At this point you should understand the core AngularJS concepts and terminology. Time to brew a fresh pot and get to work.</p>

<p><img src="/images/french_press.jpg" alt="AngularJS Fuel - Photo Credit: Bjørn Giesenbauer" /></p>

<p>If you are anything like me, by now you&rsquo;re ready to dig into a <strong>proper example application</strong>. Luckily we have the excellent <a href="https://github.com/angular-app/angular-app">angular-app</a> project to explore. This non-trivial example focuses on best practices for:</p>

<ul>
<li>Folder structure (important!)</li>
<li>Modules (very important!)</li>
<li><strong>Testing</strong> (super important!)</li>
<li>RESTful services</li>
<li>Navigation</li>
<li>Security</li>
</ul>


<p>angular-app combines a solid AngularJS UI with a node.js backend. It is non-trivial, and studying this app will give you a realistic sense of a proper AngularJS app.</p>

<p>One killer aspect of this example is the build system. It <strong>demonstrates a fantastic Grunt.js build with an integrated Karma Test Runner</strong>.</p>

<p>Peter Bacon Darwin and Pewel Kozlowski have done a great job. Front to back, this project is worth your study time. You could spend several days investigating the nooks and crannies of this example, but we&rsquo;ve only got the weekend. Set angular-app to the side for now, but keep it handy. It will serve as valuable reference in the future.</p>

<h2>Start building your own app with ng-boilerplate ~4hrs</h2>

<p>At this point you should have a solid knowledge to start building something. The <a href="https://github.com/joshdmiller/ng-boilerplate">ng-boilerplate</a> project will get you started. <strong>This is the seed you should use</strong>. It takes the lessons you learned studying angular-app, and provides the foundation upon which to build something substantial.</p>

<p><img src="/images/engine.jpg" alt="a strong engine for your AngularJS app" /></p>

<p>ng-boilerplate, unlike the angular-seed project, is <strong>suitable as a starting point for building a production app</strong>. It&rsquo;s a solid shortcut, and worth study.</p>

<p>Spend some time getting to know ng-boilerplate through its excellent README. The READMEs don&rsquo;t stop at the root of the project. Josh has sprinkled them throughout the project to help you understand what is going on.</p>

<p>Once you have your head around ng-boilerplate, you can delete all of the placeholder views, and <strong>start trying things out for yourself</strong>.</p>

<p>Need some ideas?</p>

<ul>
<li>PRISM:Refract &ndash; NSA Dashboard</li>
<li>FlySwatter &ndash; A simple bug tracker</li>
<li>GeekTalk &ndash; Multiroom Chat</li>
<li>OctoStats &ndash; Ranked Github Users with Clever D3 Visuals</li>
<li>1000words &ndash; Writing app that sets target of 1000 words per day and graphs your success</li>
<li>GetItDone &ndash; Yup, a todo list.</li>
<li>&hellip;?</li>
</ul>


<p>The sky is the limit. Using the reference material you&rsquo;ve studied all weekend, combined with the official AngularJS docs, you should be well on the way to AngularJS mastery. You&rsquo;ll be over the hump, having defeated that infamous curve. Build something cool and tell me about it.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve hit any road blocks, <a href="https://mail.google.com/mail/?view=cm&amp;fs=1&amp;tf=1&amp;to=joelhooks@gmail.com&amp;su=Hello,%can%I%20get%20some%20help?">send me an email</a> and I&rsquo;ll help you out.</p>

<h2>Congrats! You&rsquo;ve leveled up.</h2>

<p>The fun isn&rsquo;t over. There is <strong>plenty left to learn</strong>. The weekend <em>is</em> over though, and you&rsquo;ve worked hard. Take a break and relax.</p>

<p>You&rsquo;ve earned it.</p>

<p><img src="/images/yellow_belt.jpg" alt="You've Leveled up your AngularJS! - Photo Credit: Cayusa" /></p>

<p>P.S. Initial project setup is one of the most critical factors to a project&rsquo;s success. Using templates is a great way to get a head start, but using a template without solid understanding of all the moving parts can be dangerous. I&rsquo;m working on <strong>step-by-step guide to building your own best practices AngularJS project template</strong>. If you want to get notified of its progress, as well as launch-day discounts, sign up to my newsletter below.</p>

<p>You might also enjoy: <a href="http://joelhooks.com/blog/2013/05/22/lessons-learned-kicking-off-an-angularjs-project/"><strong>Lessons Learned: A Year with a Large AngularJS Project</strong></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The basics of using ui-router with AngularJS]]></title>
    <link href="http://joelhooks.com/blog/2013/07/22/the-basics-of-using-ui-router-with-angularjs/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-22T10:55:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://joelhooks.com/blog/2013/07/22/the-basics-of-using-ui-router-with-angularjs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>URL routing is a popular approach to matching the contents of a URL to specific
functionality within a web application. URL routes programatically present
specific content to users based on the URL that they are visiting. It is a
popular approach that has proven to be very effective.</p>

<p>Something that might not be obvious is that URL routing is also a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finite-state_machine">finite state
machine</a>. When you configure
the routing for an app, you are laying out the various states the application
can be in, and informing the application what to display and do when a specific
route is encountered.</p>

<p>AngularJS supplies <a href="http://docs.angularjs.org/tutorial/step_07">URL routing</a> by default.
It is adequate, but also has some limitations.</p>

<p><img src="/images/app-layout.png" alt="A resonable application structure" /></p>

<h2>So what&rsquo;s the problem?</h2>

<p>Looking at the structure above, imagine an application where interacting with
items on the header or the sidebar causes the main content to load completely
different HTML. AngularJS provides a mechanism for this with <code>ng-switch</code>. You
can see a (very simple) example of this below.</p>

<iframe width="100%" height="300"
  src="http://jsfiddle.net/joelhooks/Swm48/4/embedded/result,js,html"
  allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" frameborder="0"></iframe>


<p>In this case, <code>ng-switch</code> is swapping out <code>div</code> elements, but you can also use
this approach to swap out templates using <code>ng-include</code>.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not going to explore this option. I&rsquo;m not particularly fond of it.</p>

<p><strong>Why not?</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>The <code>ng-switch</code> adds markup that could be confusing</li>
<li>The state of the main content area is captured and stored on a model</li>
<li>It feels like &ldquo;logic in markup&rdquo;, which I try to avoid</li>
<li>If you go down the <code>ng-include</code> road, you need to remember to always put
single quotes around your template names. I always forget. ;&lt;</li>
</ul>


<h2>ui-router</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/angular-ui/ui-router">ui-router</a> fully embraces the
state-machine nature of a routing system. It allows you to define states, and
transition your application to those states. The real win is that it allows you
to decouple nested states, and do some very complicated layouts in an elegant
way.</p>

<p>You need to think about your routing a bit differently, but once you get your
head around the state-based approach, I think you will like it.</p>

<iframe width="100%" height="300"
  src="http://jsfiddle.net/SvUjA/1/embedded/result,js,html"
  allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" frameborder="0"></iframe>


<p>This example is functionally very similar to the <code>ng-switch</code> approach. The main
difference is that the main content area is populated with templated HTML for
each of the states, without using switching or <code>ng-include</code>.</p>

<p>``` javascript
angular.module(&lsquo;app&rsquo;, [&lsquo;ui.compat&rsquo;])</p>

<pre><code>.config(['$stateProvider', function ($stateProvider) {
    var home = {
            name: 'home',
            url: '/',
            templateUrl: 'content.html'
        },
        red = {
            name: 'red',
            url: '/red',
            parent: home,
            templateUrl: 'content.red.html'
        },
        blue = {
            name: 'blue',
            url: '/blue',
            parent: home,
            templateUrl: 'content.blue.html'
        },
        green = {
            name: 'green',
            url: '/green',
            parent: home,
            templateUrl: 'content.green.html'
        };

    $stateProvider.state(home);
    $stateProvider.state(red);
    $stateProvider.state(green);
    $stateProvider.state(blue);
}])
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>The above code is the configuration for the router. We are defining the <code>module</code>, but instead
of injecting <code>$routeProvider</code> as we would with stock AngularJS, we are injecting
a <code>$stateProvider</code> that is used to define the states. We are defining 4 states.</p>

<ul>
<li><code>home</code> is the parent state of the next 3. It defines the header, siderbar, and
the <code>ui-view</code> element that will be populated with the child states.</li>
<li><code>red</code> is the first child state. It references the <code>home</code> as its parent, as
well as targeting its own template.</li>
<li><code>blue</code> and <code>green</code> are identical to <code>red</code>, but use different templates.</li>
</ul>


<p>After the states are defined, they are added to the <code>$stateProvider</code>. They are
now ready to be navigated to.</p>

<p>``` javascript</p>

<pre><code>.run(['$state', function ($state) {
   $state.transitionTo('home'); 
}])
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>the <code>run</code> method is a great place to navigate to your intial state. You are able to
inject the now-resolved <code>$state</code> object and use its <code>transitionTo</code> method to set <code>home</code>
as the current state.</p>

<p>``` javascript</p>

<pre><code>.controller('SidebarCtrl', function ($scope, $state) {

$scope.content = ['red', 'green', 'blue'];

$scope.setPage = function (page) {
    $state.transitionTo(page);
};
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>The <code>SidebarCtrl</code> lists contains a simple array called content on its <code>$scope</code> which
is used in a <code>ng-repeat</code> to give us a simple menu. When one of those items is clicked
the <code>setPage</code> function is called with the item that was clicked. In this case, the
content items correspond to the names of the states that we&rsquo;ve defined, so we simply
<code>transitionTo</code> the selected state to display the content of that state.</p>

<h2>Next steps with ui-router</h2>

<p>This only really scratches the very surface of what you can pull off with
ui-router. There are a ton of options and the
<a href="https://github.com/angular-ui/ui-router/wiki">wiki</a> is well put together. Some
things I didn&rsquo;t explore, but that are available:</p>

<ul>
<li>Passing data between states</li>
<li>Listening for state events</li>
<li>Named views (love this, it deserves its own post)</li>
<li>URL Routing</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>The ui-router README warns that the utility is still in active early
development</strong>. The API is still subject to change, so if you choose ui-router for
your next project, that is something to be aware of.</p>

<p>Let me know if you&rsquo;d like me to explore ui-router a bit deeper in future posts.
I think it is an excellent approach to routing, and look forward to using it
more.</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> I&rsquo;ve recorded a <a href="http://egghead.io/lessons/angularjs-introduction-ui-router">screencast about ui-router</a> for egghead.io.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
