<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: spa | Joel Hooks]]></title>
  <link href="http://joelhooks.com/blog/categories/spa/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://joelhooks.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-11T15:56:11-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://joelhooks.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joel Hooks]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learn AngularJS this Weekend]]></title>
    <link href="http://joelhooks.com/blog/2013/08/03/learn-angularjs-in-a-weekend/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-03T23:36:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://joelhooks.com/blog/2013/08/03/learn-angularjs-in-a-weekend</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>AngularJS has a reputation for a steep learning curve. It&rsquo;s definitely complex, but follows the 80/20 rule. <strong>20% of the features are what you will use 80% of the time</strong>. If you are new to AngularJS and have a weekend to study, there are some very high quality resources that will let you <strong>start Monday with a strong working knowledge of AngularJS</strong>.</p>

<p>Already know AngularJS? Feel free to skip ahead. These resources are excellent, and you&rsquo;re bound to learn something.</p>

<h2>The Official Tutorial ~4hrs</h2>

<p>Start with <a href="http://docs.angularjs.org/tutorial">the official tutorial</a>. It provides a very straight forward overview of AngularJS and walks step by step through building a simple app. When you&rsquo;re done, you should have <strong>a solid understanding of the basics</strong> and the vocabulary you will need to move on to the next step.</p>

<p>The official tutorial is <em>very</em> well put together. Unfortunately it utilizes the angular-seed project as a template. The angular-seed project is fine for quickly throwing together a working AngularJS app, but it doesn&rsquo;t provide a structure that scales well in a production application.</p>

<p><strong>Don&rsquo;t use the angular-seed to start your real projects!</strong> It&rsquo;s a learning tool only.</p>

<h2>Kickass (<strong>free!</strong>) Video Tutorials on Egghead.io ~3hrs</h2>

<div style="float: left; padding:10px;"><a class="nofancybox" href="http://egghead.io"><div style=" height: 191px; width: 150px; background-image: url(/images/egghead_logo.png);"></div></a></div>


<p>You&rsquo;ve done the tutorial, and should have a good grasp of the basics. Your next stop is John Lindquist&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.egghead.io/">egghead.io for free AngularJS videos</a>. This series of bite-sized videos will deliver a ton of great information. John has gone through almost all of the &ldquo;hard&rdquo; concepts, and presented them in an easy to understand way.</p>

<p><em>All</em> of the videos are great, but the <strong>series on directives is extra fantastic</strong>. Transclusion? No problem. Even after using AngularJS for over a year, I was able to solidify some of the concepts that were confusing for me.</p>

<p>Watch them all and <strong>take some notes</strong>. When you come out of the other side your AngularJS-fu will be starting to take shape.</p>

<p><img src="/images/lemonade.jpg" alt="ahhhhhhh Learning AngularJS is refreshing - Photo Credit: chotda" /></p>

<p>That will take you through Saturday evening, and you deserve a rest. <strong>Send John a donation for his hard work</strong>, pour a tall glass of lemonade, and relax as you reflect on the your new-found knowledge of an awesome framework. Nice work!</p>

<h2>Things get real with angular-app ~4hrs</h2>

<p>Sunday morning.</p>

<p>At this point you should understand the core AngularJS concepts and terminology. Time to brew a fresh pot and get to work.</p>

<p><img src="/images/french_press.jpg" alt="AngularJS Fuel - Photo Credit: Bjørn Giesenbauer" /></p>

<p>If you are anything like me, by now you&rsquo;re ready to dig into a <strong>proper example application</strong>. Luckily we have the excellent <a href="https://github.com/angular-app/angular-app">angular-app</a> project to explore. This non-trivial example focuses on best practices for:</p>

<ul>
<li>Folder structure (important!)</li>
<li>Modules (very important!)</li>
<li><strong>Testing</strong> (super important!)</li>
<li>RESTful services</li>
<li>Navigation</li>
<li>Security</li>
</ul>


<p>angular-app combines a solid AngularJS UI with a node.js backend. It is non-trivial, and studying this app will give you a realistic sense of a proper AngularJS app.</p>

<p>One killer aspect of this example is the build system. It <strong>demonstrates a fantastic Grunt.js build with an integrated Karma Test Runner</strong>.</p>

<p>Peter Bacon Darwin and Pewel Kozlowski have done a great job. Front to back, this project is worth your study time. You could spend several days investigating the nooks and crannies of this example, but we&rsquo;ve only got the weekend. Set angular-app to the side for now, but keep it handy. It will serve as valuable reference in the future.</p>

<h2>Start building your own app with ng-boilerplate ~4hrs</h2>

<p>At this point you should have a solid knowledge to start building something. The <a href="https://github.com/joshdmiller/ng-boilerplate">ng-boilerplate</a> project will get you started. <strong>This is the seed you should use</strong>. It takes the lessons you learned studying angular-app, and provides the foundation upon which to build something substantial.</p>

<p><img src="/images/engine.jpg" alt="a strong engine for your AngularJS app" /></p>

<p>ng-boilerplate, unlike the angular-seed project, is <strong>suitable as a starting point for building a production app</strong>. It&rsquo;s a solid shortcut, and worth study.</p>

<p>Spend some time getting to know ng-boilerplate through its excellent README. The READMEs don&rsquo;t stop at the root of the project. Josh has sprinkled them throughout the project to help you understand what is going on.</p>

<p>Once you have your head around ng-boilerplate, you can delete all of the placeholder views, and <strong>start trying things out for yourself</strong>.</p>

<p>Need some ideas?</p>

<ul>
<li>PRISM:Refract &ndash; NSA Dashboard</li>
<li>FlySwatter &ndash; A simple bug tracker</li>
<li>GeekTalk &ndash; Multiroom Chat</li>
<li>OctoStats &ndash; Ranked Github Users with Clever D3 Visuals</li>
<li>1000words &ndash; Writing app that sets target of 1000 words per day and graphs your success</li>
<li>GetItDone &ndash; Yup, a todo list.</li>
<li>&hellip;?</li>
</ul>


<p>The sky is the limit. Using the reference material you&rsquo;ve studied all weekend, combined with the official AngularJS docs, you should be well on the way to AngularJS mastery. You&rsquo;ll be over the hump, having defeated that infamous curve. Build something cool and tell me about it.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve hit any road blocks, <a href="https://mail.google.com/mail/?view=cm&amp;fs=1&amp;tf=1&amp;to=joelhooks@gmail.com&amp;su=Hello,%can%I%20get%20some%20help?">send me an email</a> and I&rsquo;ll help you out.</p>

<h2>Congrats! You&rsquo;ve leveled up.</h2>

<p>The fun isn&rsquo;t over. There is <strong>plenty left to learn</strong>. The weekend <em>is</em> over though, and you&rsquo;ve worked hard. Take a break and relax.</p>

<p>You&rsquo;ve earned it.</p>

<p><img src="/images/yellow_belt.jpg" alt="You've Leveled up your AngularJS! - Photo Credit: Cayusa" /></p>

<p>P.S. Initial project setup is one of the most critical factors to a project&rsquo;s success. Using templates is a great way to get a head start, but using a template without solid understanding of all the moving parts can be dangerous. I&rsquo;m working on <strong>step-by-step guide to building your own best practices AngularJS project template</strong>. If you want to get notified of its progress, as well as launch-day discounts, sign up to my newsletter below.</p>

<p>You might also enjoy: <a href="http://joelhooks.com/blog/2013/05/22/lessons-learned-kicking-off-an-angularjs-project/"><strong>Lessons Learned: A Year with a Large AngularJS Project</strong></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
